# **Dinesh Sainath**

dineshsainath.github.io/Portfolio/ | ds1025287@gmail.com | +91 9003253322

#### SUMMARY

A motivated Software Developer with 2 years of internship experience in designing and developing web applications. Proficient in Wireframing, Prototyping in Figma, React, JavaScript, HTML & CSS modern front-end tools, inculcating design principles, testing, WCAG Accessibility, developing products adhering to the requirements and pleasing the aesthetics.

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Tech: HTML5, CSS3, Java, JavaScript, Typescript, jQuery, NoSQL, MongoDB.
- Frameworks: ReactJs, Redux, Node js, Express.js, Es6 Tools: Visual Studio, Figma, Jira, Confluence, Adobe Photoshop,
- SDLC's: Agile (Scrum). Build Tools: Git, Gitlab, Linux.

### EDUCATIONAL BACKGROUND

## UNIVERSITY OF GUELPH, Ontario, Canada – Bachelor of Computer Science Engineering

2017 - 2022

- UoG Entrance Scholarship of \$13000 for outstanding academic achievement.
- Best prototype project for System Analysis and Design in Applications.

#### WEB DEVELOPMENT BOOTCAMP, Udemy

2021

CHETTINAD VIDYASHRAM, Chennai, India - High School

2014 - 2017

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

#### GRAVVITY, Toronto - Software Developer Intern

04/2023 - Present

- Constructed requirements, wireframes & prototype by collaborating with the CEO, COO & business partners.
- Led the wireframe design mock-ups with animations and touchscreen interactions using Figma and Sketch adhering to WCAG 2.1
   AA and AODA compliance. Collaborated with the CEO to translate complex functionalities into user-friendly design.
- Developed interfaces and functionalities of e-commerce for research and advancement towards virtual reality systems.
- Produced 20+ visual elements by translating UI/UX responsive design wireframes into reusable code components using React, Bootstrap, Material UI (MUI), Typescript and ES6 Features.

## VANKAY SYSTEMS, Raleigh, North Carolina -Web Developer Intern

07/2022 - 01/2023

- Developed reusable components for user interface using React JS, Forms, Props and React Hooks reducing support tickets by 31%.
- Collaborated with backend developers to integrate RESTful APIs, ensuring data retrieval, payment getaways and real-time
  updates optimizing CICD pipeline increasing performance by 27% monitored through KPI Tracking tools.
- Implemented es6 functionalities and optimized user interfaces using React, HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.

## **VANKAY SYSTEMS**, Raleigh, North Carolina – Web Developer Intern

01/2020 - 06/2020

- Created forms to collect and validate data from the user in React components.
- Analyzed 30+ user requirements to derive technical UX/UI software design and performance requirements.
- Collaborated with senior developers to draw documentation for code, guidelines, and best practices to ensure consistency and code maintainability across projects.

## **ICOMMUNITY**, University of Toronto – *Research Intern*

08/2020 - 01/2021

- Created user-friendly interfaces using WordPress CMS to customize themes and develop custom plugins.
- Researched with the marketing team to design user interface & content management system with MailChimp.

## **PROJECTS**

#### **Keeper** - https://codesandbox.io/s/keeper-pjv54

 Developed a web application that takes note cards with a title and content section developed using React hooks, components, conditional rendering and utilized array of objects to add, edit and delete note cards.

## **Profile Deck** - https://coruscating-crostata-d691f8.netlify.app/

• Developed a web application that parses JSON REST API into card components and displays user profiles rendered using React incorporating ES6, hooks, conditional rendering for dynamic search including tags.

#### The Grove - https://rb.gy/x7ztqq

 Created a web application GUI prototype on Figma by wireframing various screens for a Youth foundation to facilitate streamlined communication between the youth and subject matter experts.